Today's דף daf *daf* is דף כד *daf kaf-daled*.
We take it from the very top. We have moved on to
other areas of what is true for A is not true for
B and vice versa. We are comparing the פרה אדומה parah adumah?
*Parah Adumah* and the עגלה ערופה eglah arufah *Eglah Arufah*, two things
done with cows in a ritual way outside of the מקדש Mikdash,
*Mikdash*. And we say one of them you שחט *shecht* and the
other one you do עריפה arifah *arifah*, you break the neck, and
not vice versa. And we know you only do שחיטה shchita, *shechitah*
by the פרה אדומה parah adumah. *Parah Adumah* because it says ושחט
*veshachat* and it also says חוקה chukah. *chukah*, זאת חוקת התורה *zot
chukat hatorah*. So therefore it can be nothing other than שחיטה shchita
*shechitah*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* picks up two lines from the
top on דף כד עמוד א *daf kaf-daled amud aleph*. וכל היכא
*vechol hecha* says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, וכל היכא דכתיב dechtiv, ביה
חוקה *vechol hecha dichsiv bei chuka*, anytime are you telling me anytime
the תורה Torah *Torah* says חוק chok *chok*, לא דרשינן קל וחומר
darshinan kal va-chomer? *lo darshenan kal vachomer*? We don't make a קל
וחומר kal va-chomer *kal vachomer*, because remember חוק chok *chok* was a
big word we used a lot in זבחים Zevachim, *Zevachim* to tell
me that this criteria is מעכב *meakeiv*. This criteria must be done,
you can't forgo it. But that's different from saying that you can't
add to it or give alternatives. Here we're trying to use a
קל וחומר kal va-chomer, *kal vachomer* to say not that שחיטה shchita.
*shechitah* isn't required but that based on a קל וחומר kal va-chomer
*kal vachomer*, in addition to שחיטה shchita. *shechitah*, as an alternative to
שחיטה shchita. *shechitah*, you could also do עריפה arifah *arifah*. So we
never said that חוק chok, *chok* prevents you from using a קל
וחומר kal va-chomer. *kal vachomer*. How do you now, והא ve-ha גבי
יום הכפורים *v'ha gabi Yom HaKippurim*, and I'll show you this because
when it comes to יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*, דכתיב ביה
חוקה *dichsiv bei chuka*, it says חוק *chok* by יום כיפור *Yom
Kippur*, right? That's a major word that it says by יום כיפור
*Yom Kippur*.
And nevertheless we use a קל וחומר kal va-chomer. *kal vachomer*. How
do we know? Because of the following. Right by
יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* it says, what does it say by the
way by חוק *chok* by יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*? It says, what
does it say by יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*?
Michael? Thank you. Ah, okay. I thought you were going to tell
me Michael.
By יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* it says, it's the very end of
the פרשה parsha *parsha* it says,
ויעשה זאת לכם לחוקת עולם *ve-asah zot lachem le-chukat olam*, no, what
does it say by יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*? שבת שבתון היא לכם
ועניתם את
נפשותיכם חוקת עולם *Shabbat Shabbaton hi
lachem ve-innitem et nafshoteichem chukat olam*. Okay so it says חוק *chok*
by יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*. ועניתם את נפשותיכם *ve-innitem et nafshoteichem*, that's
true. I think it says חוקת עולם *chukat olam* anyway. But anyway
it says חוק *chok* by יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*, and if anybody's
gone through יומא *Yoma* you learned you know that we use that
word חוק *chok* to tell me that so many of the details
of יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* are מעכב *meakeiv*. And nevertheless we're going
to use a קל וחומר kal va-chomer *kal vachomer*. והא גבי יום
הכפורים דכתיב ביה חוקה *v'ha gabi Yom HaKippurim dichsiv bei chuka*, it
says חוק *chok*, דתניא *detanya* we taught in the ברייתא braisa *braita*,
ועשהו חטאת chatas. *veasahu chattat*. This is by you draw the lots
and of the two goats and the one that the name of
God comes above is the חטאת *chattat* and the one that the
name of the עזאזל *Azazel* goes above that becomes the one that's
pushed off the cliff.
Okay, והיתה זאת לכם לחוקת עולם *vehayetah zot lachem le-chukat olam*, thank
you, that's the one I was thinking about. Thank you. ויעשה זאת
לכם לחוקת עולם *ve-asah zot lachem le-chukat olam*, right. Okay, so anyway
ועשהו חטאת *veasahu chattat*, and from there we learn הגורל עושה חטאת
*hagoral oseh chattat*, so it's the drawing of the lot that determines
which of the goats is the חטאת *chattat* and which of the
one is לעזאזל *l'azazel*, ואין השם עושה חטאת v'ein ha-shem oseh chatas
*v'ein hashem oseh chattat*, that just declaring if somebody were to say
להשם *l'Hashem* or להשם חטאת *l'Hashem chattat* or you know whatever that
would not create the designation. The designation of the two goats, which
one goes as the offering to השם *Hashem* and which one gets
pushed off the cliff, that's all done by the drawing of the
lots. It cannot come through verbal declaration. Certainly not verbal declaration alone.
Okay now שיכול *sheyachol*, and the ברייתא *braita* goes on it says
I might have thought דלא דין הוא *delo din hu*, I would
have made a קל וחומר kal va-chomer *kal vachomer* to say that
it can be decided by verbal declaration. Why? ומה במקום שלא קידש
הגורל קידש השם *umah bemakom shelo kideish hagoral kideish hashem*,
when there's no such thing as גורל *goral* nevertheless declaring something as
a קרבן korban? *korban* works. So for example, the example that רש''י
Rashi *Rashi* gives is if you have two, you have something somewhat
similar to this where when you bring two birds as a קרבן
korban *korban*, one is a חטאת *chattat* and one is an עולה
*olah*, you can designate the two birds as a group and only
when you finally get to bringing them to the כהן Kohen *Kohen*
you can say this is the חטאת *chattat*, this is the עולה
*olah*, or sometimes even the כהן Kohen *Kohen* based on what he
does determines which is the חטאת *chattat* and the עולה *olah*. So
there it's done by declaration and it's not done by lot. If
you were to have lots and say one would say חטאת *chattat*
and one would say עולה *olah* over your two birds that would
not create the קדושה *kedushah* and would not designate which is the
חטאת *chattat* which is the עולה *olah*. Okay, so there we only
know that verbal declaration works, we do not know that what do
you call it, that lots work. So there מה במקום שלא קידש
הגורל קידש השם *umah bemakom shelo kideish hagoral kideish hashem* where lots
do not sanctify, declaring something a חטאת *chattat* or an עולה *olah*
does sanctify. מקום שקידש הגורל *makom shekideish hagoral* here by the goats
where the lots sanctify determine which is the one for the קרבן
korban *korban* and which is off the cliff, אינו דין שתהא השם
מקדש Mikdash *eino din shetehei hashem mekadeish* much more so should a
verbal declaration work? So therefore that stands to reason and maybe we
would say that? תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar, *talmud lomar* so therefore the
verse had to say ועשהו *veasahu*
again with the personal pronoun you shall make it חטאת *chattat*, so
only, only, you know it only comes through the making of a
חטאת *chattat*, it only, only the גורל *goral* makes it a חטאת
*chattat* and nothing else. הגורל עושה חטאת *hagoral oseh chattat*. only the
lots make a חטאת ואין השם עושה חטאת and not a verbal
declaration. Okay, so what we learn is that you don't say your
קל וחומר kal va-chomer to use the verbal declaration. But the גמרא
Gemara says that's only because you had a פסוק. pasuk. Without a
פסוק, pasuk, I would have used a קל וחומר, kal va-chomer? even
though by יום כיפור there's a principle of חוק and everything has
to be done exactly so. Exactly so means you can't just forgo
it, but it doesn't mean you can't use a קל וחומר kal
va-chomer, to determine what types of things are possibilities. So הלאו, halav,
so the גמרא Gemara says טעמא, ta'ama, the reason that you do
not use declaration and you only use lots is דכתיב רחמנא ועשהו
חטאת d'kasiv rachmana v'asahu chatas because the verse said explicitly it shall
make it, the lot shall make it into a חטאת. There's an
explicit verse. הלאו הכי, halav hachi, was there not that explicit verse,
דרשינן קל וחומר? kal va-chomer, So you would have used a קל
וחומר. So we see, although חוק means, as I said, that you
cannot forgo a requirement, it does not prevent you from using a
קל וחומר. So we're back to our question: How do you know
that you cannot do the עריפה arifah by a פרה אדומה? parah
adumah. It's true it says שחיטה, it's true it says חוק, but
let's make a קל וחומר from the עגלה ערופה eglah arufah. and
say that עריפה arifah also works, breaking the neck works for פרה
אדומה. parah adumah So the גמרא Gemara, says, alright, well try another
one. מיעט רחמנא. mi'eit rachmana. You're right, it's not based on the
word חוקה. מיעט רחמנא גבי עגלה הערופה, mi'eit rachmana gabi eglah ha-arufah,
the תורה Torah says by the calf where you break the neck
הערופה. ha-arufah.
It says עגלה הערופה בנחל, eglah ha-arufah banachal,
the one with the broken neck. So ה ha is a, what's
the word? A direct, yeah, right, what's how do you define a
definite article? Thank you. ה ha is a definite article. It's the
one with the broken neck and there's no other with a broken
neck. So that's how we learn you do not break the neck
for any other type of a ritual thing, even outside of the
המקדש. ha-Mikdash. It's הערופה, ha-arufah, only this is the one with the
broken neck. זאת בעריפה ואין אחרת בעריפה, Zot ba-arifah v'ein acheres ba-arifah,
this one with the breaking of the neck,
nothing else with the breaking of the neck, not even פרה, parah,
not a פרה אדומה. parah adumah, Okay, fine. Now that's how we
know פרה אדומה parah adumah you don't break the neck. How about
the reverse? ותהא עגלה כשירה בשחיטה מקל וחומר? v'sehei eglah ksheirah b'shchita
mi-kal va-chomer?
Fine, now that we know you don't break the neck of the
פרה אדומה, let's try the קל וחומר the opposite way and say
you could do שחיטה for the עגלה eglah ערופה. ומה פרה שלא
הוכשרה בעריפה, u'mah parah shelo huchshra b'arifah, פרה
אדומה you cannot break the neck, כשירה בשחיטה, ksheira b'shchita, you do
a שחיטה. עגלה שכשירה בעריפה, eglah she-ksheira b'arifah, an עגלה agalah that
you can break the neck, אינו דין שהוכשרה בשחיטה? eino din she-huchshra
b'shchita? May we not say if you can break the neck, how
much more so? And there actually it's not about קל וחומר because
you would think normally the way you kill something in any type
of a ritual is by שחיטה. So maybe if the תורה Torah
does עריפה arifah you can certainly do שחיטה. So אמר קרא וערפו
העגלה, amar kra v'arfu ha-eglah,
you should do the עריפה to... again העגלה. ha-eglah. Thank you. העגלה,
ha-eglah, right, עגלה eglah, is a
wagon. וערפו העגלה, v'arfu ha-eglah, you shall break the neck of the
calf.
So בעריפה אין בשחיטה לא. ba-arifah in b'shchita lo. So it's the
עגלה, I think we're learning it... I'm trying to remember what רש"י
Rashi says what the דיוק diyuk is. It's not from העגלה. ha-eglah.
Let me see. שנה הכתוב לעכב. shina ha-kasuv l'akev. Oh, רש"י Rashi
just says it's because it repeated it. It already said you do
the עריפה and the fact that it repeated it and
said וערפו העגלה, v'arfu ha-eglah, that it already said you break the
neck and it repeated it twice is to tell you only this
way, no other way. Okay, so that's again just to show the
משנה Mishna that these two are somewhat similar, that again rituals with
cows or calves outside of the מקדש, Mikdash. but one is with
breaking of the neck, one is with שחיטה. Not too much I
think of interest here, of anything whole הוה אמינא hava amina was
strange as we said yesterday, why should you assume that certain rituals
which are distinctive you can make קל וחומר? תוספות Tosafot is very
bothered with it. תוספות Tosafot tries to sort of say, well, either
the גמרא Gemara isn't so serious about the קל וחומר, or we
have some other reason why we would have linked the two or
made a קל וחומר, but it's very hard to even understand the
הוה אמינא. hava amina. Alright, let's go on now to the next
case
and something again still somewhat in the קדשים Kodashim world, but certainly
a nice shift. כשר בכהנים פסול בלויים. Kasher b'Kohanim pasul b'Levi'im.
The things that make a כהן Kohen. כשר kasher are a כהן
Kohen. could be כשר kasher with certain issues for which a לוי
Levi would be פסול, pasul, would not be able to do the
עבודה. avodah. כשר בלויים פסול בכהנים. Kasher b'Levi'im pasul b'Kohanim. There are
things that a לוי Levi would be כשר kasher with which are
not a problem for a לוי, Levi, פסול בכהנים, pasul b'Kohanim, which
would be problems for a כהן. Kohen So what are they? And
we can sort of guess what it is for the כהנים, Kohanim,
but let's take a look. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, so here's the
גמרא, Gemara the ברייתא we taught. כהנים במומין פסולין בשנים כשירים. Kohanim
b'mumin psulin, b'shanim ksheirin. כהנים Kohanim are invalid through blemishes, right? The
תורה Torah says explicit about these are the blemishes that invalidate, but
if their age, if there's no sense of being too old to
be a
כהן.
Kohen לויים, Levi'im, it says like the twenty-five...
Right, exactly, that's what we're going to get to. לויים, Levi'im, the
flip is true by the לויים. Levi'im. במומין כשירים, b'mumin ksheirin, blemishes
are not a problem,
בשנים פסולין, b'shanim psulin, but age is a problem, because the תורה
Torah says when it counts the לויים Levi'im that it counts them
between thirty and fifty. And actually it says that when they're over
50 it says ולא יעבד עוד *velov ya'avod od*, ישוב מצבא העבודה
*yashuv mitzva ha'avoda*, they'll go back from there the army of their
service and they will no longer serve. So by לויים Levi'im *Levi'im*
there's an age of 30 to 50 the Torah says and it
does not appear by the כהנים Kohanim. *Kohanim*, the כהנים Kohanim, *Kohanim*
only appears blemishes. Okay, now they're actually of all the cases where
you would have said maybe we should apply one to the other,
here's a place I think you would have thought, right? Because here's
not like a ritual characteristic of an object, like does it have
to be old? This קרבן korban *korban* is old, this is young,
this is male, this is female, this you do שחיטה *shechita*, this
you do עריפה *arifa*. Here's an idea that the Torah is saying
like these things are problems, right? Too old is a problem, blemishes
are a problem, and you know these are both people that serve
in the מקדש Mikdash *Mikdash*. So there could have been a logic
to say maybe it's, you know, you apply them from one to
the other. So there the משנה Mishna, *Mishnah* says no, each one
is true for its own category. What?
One is a subset of the other.
Another good point. So if a לוי Levi *Levi*, right, a כהן
Kohen *Kohen* could also be invalid qua לוי Levi *Levi* you're saying.
Right, maybe כהן Kohen *Kohen* has more requirements but why should he
have fewer requirements? Very good point. So let's take a look at
the, at the, you know, how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* develops this.
מנא הני מילי *mena hani milei*, where do you know this from?
דתנו רבנן Detanu Rabbanan *detanu rabanan*, we taught: זאת אשר ללוים *Zot
asher la-Levi'im*, this is for the לויים Levi'im *Levi'im*. מה תלמוד לומר
*mah talmud lomar*, what is the point of that? לפי שנאמר shenemar,
*lefi shene'emar*, because it says: ומבן חמשים שנה ישוב *umiben hamishim shanah
yashuv*, from 50 years he shall return. So let me just read
you those פסוקים psukim *pesukim*. This is in בהעלותך *Behaalotecha* where it
speaks about, you know, taking out the לויים Levi'im *Levi'im* and sanctifying
them and doing waving them, dedicating them for the temple service. So
after it speaks about the ritual of dedicating them it says the
following: וידבר ה' אל משה לאמר *vayidaber Hashem el Moshe lemor*, זאת
אשר ללוים *Zot asher la-Levi'im*, this is the law. מבן חמש ועשרים
שנה ומעלה mi-ben chamesh ve-esrim shanah va-ma'alah, יבוא לצבוא צבא litzvo tzava.
בעבודת אהל מועד Ohel Moed. *miben hamesh ve'esrim shanah va-ma'alah yavo litzvo
tzava ba'avodat ohel mo'ed*, from 25 on they shall come, it's interesting
the imagery, לצבוא litzvo צבא *litzvo tzava*, like serve in the army
in the service of אהל מועד Ohel Moed, *Ohel Mo'ed*. Right, because
by בני ישראל Yisrael *Bnei Yisrael* when they're counted from 20 years
up, כל היוצא לצבא *kol hayotzei latzava*, the army, that's the literal
army. You know, there's a reason why like חב"ד *Chabad* has this
idea of צבאות השם *Tzivot Hashem*, right, serving in God's army. Anyway,
it is a little bit strange though, you know, this militaristic imagery
within serving in the מקדש Mikdash, *Mikdash*, but maybe it's to sort
of say, you know, they're no lesser in what they do to
serve the people than those that are in the army. But anyway
when they're counted when the people are counted 20 years up it's
כל היוצא לצבא *kol hayotzei latzava* and when the לויים Levi'im *Levi'im*
are counted it's לצבוא צבא *litzvo tzava* to serve in the army
in the עבודת אהל מועד Ohel Moed. *avodat Ohel Mo'ed*. ומבן חמשים
שנה ישוב מצבא העבודה *umiben hamishim shanah yashuv mitzva ha'avoda* and from
50 over 50 years he shall return from the army of service,
ולא יעבד עוד *velov ya'avod od* and no service. ושרת את אחיו
באהל מועד לשמר משמרת *vesheret et echav be'ohel mo'ed lishmor mishmeret*, the
פסוק *pasuk* says he can serve with his brothers to protect the
אהל מועד Ohel Moed *Ohel Mo'ed*, meaning to be on guard duty.
ועבודה לא יעבוד *va'avoda lo ya'avod* but he can't do service, which
presumably means the carrying of the משכן *Mishkan*, maybe the singing that
accompanies the קרבנות korbanot, *korbanot*. He can serve, he can be guard
but not service. ככה תעשה ללוים במשמרתם *kacha ta'aseh la-Levi'im bemishmerotam*. So
these פסוקים *pesukim* seem very clear from 25 to 50. This is
a little problem. If anybody knows remembers the beginning of נשא *Naso*
and the end of במדבר *Bamidbar* where the לויים Levi'im *Levi'im* are
counted, they're counted from שלשים שנה ועד חמשים שנה *shloshim shanah ve'ad
hamishim shanah*. כל הבא לצבוא צבא kol haba litzvo tzava. בעבודת אהל
מועד *kol haba litzvo tzava ba'avodat ohel mo'ed*, exact same phrase, לצבוא
צבא *litzvo tzava*, serving in the service of אהל מועד *Ohel Mo'ed*,
but there it says 30 to 50. Here it says 25. And
here it seems very clearly to be telling you what the service
is. So let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*
does with it. דתנו רבנן Rabbanan *detanu rabanan*: זאת אשר ללוים *Zot
asher la-Levi'im*, this is for the לויים Levi'im *Levi'im*. מה תלמוד לומר
*mah talmud lomar*, what's the verse teaching? לפי שנאמר *lefi shene'emar*: ומבן
חמשים שנה ישוב *umiben hamishim shanah yashuv*, 50 years old and over
he shall return, למדנו ללוים שהשנים פוסלים בהם *lamadnu la-Levi'im shehashanim poslim
bahem*. We see that years invalidate if you're too old and too
young also. יכול מומין פוסלים בהם *yachol mumin poslim bahem*, maybe blemishes
are also the problem? ודין הוא *vedin hu*, and it's a קל
וחומר *kal vachomer*: ומה כהנים kohanim? שאין השנים פוסלים בהם *umah Kohanim
she'ein hashanim poslim bahem*, כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* that years are not a
problem which we don't know but we're assuming, מומין פוסלים בהם *mumin
poslim bahem* and nevertheless blemishes are problem for כהנים kohanim *Kohanim*, לויים
Levi'im שהשנים פוסלים בהם *Levi'im shehashanim פoslim bahem*, לויים Levi'im *Levi'im* that
the years are a problem, אינו דין שיהיו מומין פוסלים בהם *eino
din sheyihyu mumin poslim bahem*, how much more so should blemishes invalidate?
תלמוד לומר *talmud lomar*, the verse teaches, זאת אשר ללוים *Zot asher
la-Levi'im*. This is for the לויים Levi'im *Levi'im*, only this. זאת ללוים
*Zot la-Levi'im*, this is the only issue for the לויים Levi'im *Levi'im*,
the only criteria, ואין אחרת ללוים *ve'ein acheret la-Levi'im*. There's nothing else
that's a criteria for the לויים Levi'im *Levi'im* criterion, so blemishes are
not an issue, only this is the issue, the age. Now we're
going to do it the reverse. יכול יהו הכהנים פסולים בשנים *yachol
yehu ha-Kohanim psulim bashanim*, maybe כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* age is a problem?
והלא דין הוא *vehalo din hu*, I'll make a קל וחומר *kal
vachomer*: ומה לויים Leviim שאין מומין פוסלים בהם *umah Levi'im she'ein mumin
poslim bahem*, by לויים Leviim *Levi'im* there's not a blemish problem as
we've already established, שנים פוסלים בהם *shanim poslim bahem*, age is a
problem, כהנים kohanim שהמומין פוסלים בהם *Kohanim shehamumin poslim bahem*, by כהנים
Kohanim, *Kohanim* where blemishes are a problem, אינו דין שיהיו שנים פוסלים
בהם *eino din sheyihyu shanim poslim bahem*, how much more so should
years be a problem? If not only if even physical blemishes are
a problem, certainly age should be an issue. And as was also
added, also כהנים Kohanim, *Kohanim* are a subset of לויים Leviim *Levi'im*.
So תלמוד לומר *talmud lomar*, the verse teaches, אשר ללוים *asher la-Levi'im*.
This is what is for the לויים Leviim, *Levi'im*, ולא אשר לכהנים
*velov asher la-Kohanim*. This is the problem and it only is a
problem for the לויים Leviim, *Levi'im* and it is not a problem
for the כהנים Kohanim.
*Kohanim*. And ולא אשר לכהנים. Okay, so now we've established that for
one it's blemishes, for one it's year. I'll talk in a minute
about what that conceptually might be about, but let's first finish spelling
out the implications of this.
All of our phones are ringing these days.
One quick question. What?
Yeah.
Doesn't, aren't
there issues of just having a בעל מום Ba'al mum just at
all around in the sanctuary? Is that me? No, it's yes, yes.
Oh, I'm sorry. Sorry, I thought. Okay,
yes. Go ahead.
So there's no issue of having a בעל מום Ba'al mum just
around in the sanctuary at all?
No, not if it's not if you're a ישראל Yisrael and you're
a בעל מום, Ba'al mum, can't you bring your קרבן? korban, I
mean בעל מום Ba'al mum is only a problem to be brought
as a קרבן korban and for a כהן Kohen to do the
עבודה. avodah.
No, but to come to the.
No,
that's exactly. That's the whole point. There's no concept of מום mum
by לוים. Levi'im. It's only a concept by כהנים. Kohanim, Okay, so
we'll see about what that is in a minute. Let's talk about
them in a minute.
I guess maybe if you had a bad voice or something?
Right, exactly. Actually that's exactly correct and we'll talk about that. So
let's take a look at, so I'm going to discuss the implications
of this in a minute, but let's first finish spelling out what
the parameters are. Okay, אשר
ללוים ולא אשר לכהנים. Asher la-Levi'im velo asher la-Kohanim. יכל אף בשילה
ובבית עולמים כן? Yachol af be-Shilo uve-Veit Olamim ken? Now first of
all, the first important point is that this whole problem with the
לוים, Levi'im, which was not said in the משנה, Mishna, is only
in the אהל מועד. Right? It says מצוות עבודה בעבודת אהל מועד.
Mitzvot avodah be-avodat Ohel Moed. Once they came into ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael and they built a semi-permanent sanctuary in שילה Shilo and they
built a permanent sanctuary in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, the לוים Levi'im were not,
years was not an issue for the לוים Levi'im in that service.
Okay? How do we know? So יכל אף בשילה ובבית עולמים כן?
Yachol af be-Shilo uve-Veit Olamim ken? Maybe this this age is a
problem even
in שילה Shilo and in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, in the בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. תלמוד לומר, the verse teaches לעבוד עבודת עבודה ועבודת משא. la'avod
avodat avodah va-avodat masa. This is this is what they were given
earlier when it was said from thirty to fifty that they will
do
the work of the work and the work of carrying. So the
work of the work means the work that accompanies the עבודה. avodah.
What accompanies the עבודה? avodah? What did the לוים Levi'im do that
accompanies the עבודה? avodah? What? Clothing? No. It's the שירה. shira. They
do the singing and the playing of the musical instruments. So עבודת
עבודה avodat avodah accompanies the עבודה, avodah, the קרבנות, korbanot and the
carrying. So we are linking the two. And and the key here
is the carrying. לא אמרתי אלא מזמן שהעבודה בכתף. Lo amarti ela
mizman she-ha-avodah va-katef. This whole problem of age is only when it
includes משא, masa, carrying. Okay, once you no longer are carrying, the
place is built, it's not a sanctuary in transit, the years are
not a problem. The years are only a problem when it's which
now you understand also why years are an issue, right? Because you
have to be sort of, you know, young and healthy although you
wonder why you have to wait till thirty or twenty-five, you know,
you think of like maybe seventeen, eighteen, already that's a good age
to do it. But anyway, it's only when it's about carrying is
included in. When there's no longer carrying, years are no longer an
issue. Okay, now we're going to talk about the contradiction between twenty-five
and thirty.
So when you say עבודת עבודה ועבודת משא, avodat avodah va-avodat masa,
but when you can't do one, you can't do the other? Correct,
correct.
So when their עבודה avodah includes carrying, age is an issue. When
it doesn't include carrying, age is not an issue.
Which means they couldn't sing even though that had nothing to do
with. Correct, correct.
Although it does say they could be משמר משמרת. mishmar mishmeret. They
could do guard duty.
What does that mean exactly?
Just to make
sure that a ישראל wasn't getting too close?
Yes,
and also as the רמב"ם Rambam describes, there's also a sense of,
you know, it's a way of showing respect and honor to a
place. You know, like in England the whole thing is you have,
right, the cross, what is it, the changing of the guard and
the arm guards or whatever. You know, if it's a place that's
holy and respectful or digni- you know, something you you have guards
walking around it the whole time. So that's what they would do,
but they would not do singing.
But there was thousands of לוים, Levi'im, so.
All right, they wouldn't all be. I'm sure they had a rotation
worked out, Michael. Okay, so anyway, but the point is, so the
תורה Torah says the years were never a problem for the guard
duty. The גמרא Gemara here is saying that even the years are
not a problem for anything when there is no carrying, which is
the other major duty of the כהנים, Kohanim of the לוים, Levi'im,
is the singing. Okay. כתוב אחד
אומר. Katuv echad omer. So now did I skip? No. כתוב אחד
אומר. Katuv echad omer. Now we're going to deal with one other
another problem which I mentioned earlier. One verse says מבן חמש ועשרים
שנה ומעלה,
from twenty-five years up they shall come to serve in the army,
their army. וכתוב אחד אומר, Ve-katuv echad omer, the other verse says
מבן שלושים, mi-ben shloshim, right, all of the counting of the לוים
Levi'im was from thirty up. אי אפשר לומר שלושים, Iy efshar lomar
shloshim,
you can't say it only starts as thirty, שכבר נאמר חמש, she-kvar
ne'emar chamesh, when another verse says twenty-five. ואי אפשר לומר חמש ועשרים,
Ve-iy efshar lomar chamesh ve-esrim, you can't say it just starts at
twenty-five, שכבר נאמר שלושים. she-kvar ne'emar shloshim. It's a nice way of
just repeating the problem. הא כיצד? Ha keitzad? So how do we
resolve this? כ"ה ללמוד ושלושים לעבודה. Chaf-hei lilmod u-shloshim la-avodah. Five years
you enter into the service, actually, you know, it might be a
little bit they're emphasizing the language, because when it says twenty-five, it
says יבא לצבא עבודה, yavo litzvo avodah,
he shall come to do it, which maybe, you know, although you
have to come because he's leaving his home and he's coming to
this. But anyway לצבוא has a sense of to do it in
the future, whereas when it counts from thirty to thirty and fifty,
the language it uses is, what is the language it uses? It
says מבן שלשים שנה ועד בן חמשים שנה כל הבא לצבוא צבא.
miben shloshim shana ve'ad ben chamishim shana kol haba litzvo tzava. No,
actually it doesn't work. כל הבא לצבוא צבא. It's the exact same
words לצבוא
צבא. So forget that. Anyway, so the way they resolve it is
they say at twenty-five is when you start practicing and your boot
camp, but it's a very long boot camp, it's five years of
boot camp, and then you only work for the next twenty years
from thirty to fifty. So five years of learning the service but
not yet working in the service. What about like the כהנים? Kohanim
Yeah, that's what I...
that for the לויים Leviim.
somehow in the... There is not right there is not clearly a
rotation... there's a rotation by the מעמדות mammadot about like who
represents and stands by the קרבן but I don't think there's I
don't think we ever have a sense of a rotation
of all
לויים Leviim singing except the ones who are on guard duty.
Yeah, I don't know, meaning I don't remember, it's a good question.
I mean we never have it divided by to the best of
my knowledge I could be totally wrong about this but we don't
have it discussed about being divided in terms of houses like twenty-like
by the כהנים Kohanim, and being rotated that way. Although again I
assume that when that you have to assume that it was not
that everybody did it all the time, there was just too many
people and also, you know,
they didn't live in
ירושלים Yerushalayim and
they were... ערי לויים arei Levi'im
right, that's a
very good point too. No, there is a
discussion in תענית Ta'anit about the
מעמדות mammadot which included the לויים Leviim. but I'm not sure that
that moves the question about
whether they did
the עבודה avodah in
the בית
המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash.
It's more for the question about what do you call
it about the משמר.
mishmar.
Let me just look very quickly about that. I don't...
cause you definitely had a rotation about who represented the people in
the bringing of the regular קרבנות korbanos, but
I don't think that was the same
as...
you don't even respond to me? You're
only on
one page? Well yeah, look, here's the משנה, Mishna here's the משנה
Mishna in תענית Ta'anit and then we'll have to move on, James
you listening? The משנה mishnah in תענית Ta'anit ד׳ ב׳ daled-bet says
אלו הן מעמדות elu hen mammadot these are what the מעמדות mammadot
לפי שנאמר צו את בני ישראל ואמרת אליהם את קרבני לחמי lefi
shenemar tsav et benei Yisrael ve'amarta aleihem et korbani lachmi because היאך
קרבנו של אדם קרב והוא אינו עומד על גביו heich korbano shel
adam karev vehu eino omed al gabav
how can you bring the תמיד Tamid and you're not there? So
how do the whole people how are the entire people present for
the תמיד Tamid which is every day? התקינו נביאים ראשונים עשרים וארבעה
משמרות hitkinu nevi'im rishonim esrim ve'arba mishmarot
so here's twenty-four משמרות mishmarot which we normally associate with כהנים kohanim,
על כל משמר ומשמר היה מעמד
בירושלים al kol mishmar umishmar haya ma'amad biYrushalayim for every sort of,
you know, משמר mishmar there was a there was a group in
ירושלים Yerushalayim של כהנים של לויים ושל ישראלים shel Kohanim shel Levi'im
veshel Yisra'elim right הגיע זמן המשמר לעלות כהנים ולויים עולים לירושלים וישראל
שבאותו המשמר מתכנסין לעריהם וקורין במעשה בראשית.
higia zeman hamishmar la'alot Kohanim uLevi'im olim
liYrushalayim veYisrael shebe'oto hamishmar mitkansin le'areihem vekorin bema'aseh bereishit.
So if you think about that the it uses the this is
the whole משמר mishmar which we associate with the כהנים kohanim.
and it says that you know כהנים לויים וישראלים Kohanim Levi'im veYisra'elim
the ישראלים Yisra'elim that were close would go there to be present
but again it's not clear to me the emphasis here is about
the presence over the תמיד Tamid you know the representation it's not
clear that it means about the service in the מקדש Mikdash although
we do know for the כהנים kohanim the twenty-four משמרות mishmarot were
about the rotation in the מקדש. Mikdash So I'll have to look
look into that.
It's possible the לויים were also singing, right, that's the point.
It's possible that these משמרות mishmarot for the לויים were also a
rotation of service I just have to see if there's some discussion
about it. Okay, so let's keep on going, so they worked for
the so they they studied
for five years, they practiced for five years, it was a five
year boot camp and then they started working at the age of
thirty. Okay now the גמרא Gemara just has a little comment on
this.
כ״ה ללמוד ושלשים לעבודה kaf-hei lilmod ushloshim la-avodah מכאן mikan from here
you see לתלמיד שלא ראה סימן יפה במשנתו חמש שנים letalmid shelo
ra'ah siman yafeh bemishnato chamesh shanim that if a student is not
succeeding at working on some mastering an for five years, שוב אינו
רואה. shuv eino roeh. So then you can be assured that this
person will never succeed in this area. You should probably try another,
you may want to consider another profession if you can't master it
in five years.
You mean the דף יומי Daf Yomi
cycle is only five years? Five years. Well, no, okay, well anyway.
Well, that's why you know most professional schools are like somewhere between
three to fourth years, maybe some? All right. Yeah, exactly. Because if
it would take more than five years, you could not really be...
if you don't succeed, exactly. Now wait, the גמרא Gemara is going
to go on. Let's look at this גמרא. Gemara. שוב אינו רואה.
shuv eino roeh.
רבי יוסי אומר ג' שנים. Rabbi Yossi omer gimel shanim. Rabbi Yossi
says, no, if you can't master a, you know, a certain skill
in three years or body of knowledge, not clear if it's the
same, anyway, then you will not never succeed in that area. שנאמר,
because the verse says, ולגדלם שנים שלש, ulegadlam shanim shalosh, to raise
them for three years. This is by Daniel, right, these people that
were taken captive, the the nobles of Jerusalem that were taken captive
in בבל Bavel and that were brought into the king's court to
be raised in the king's court. So to be raised for three
years, you mean some
of the nobles?
What? Yes, the children of nobles, וללמדם ספר ולשון כשדים, ulelamdam sefer
uleshon kasdim, to teach them literature, books, and the language of the
כשדים. Kasdim. So you see for three years they had their study
program. ואידך, ve'idach, so what does the other one say that says
five years?
שאני לשון כשדים דקליל, shani lashon kasdim dekalil, no, the language of
כשדים Kasdim is an easy subject to master, so that doesn't take
three years. What about וללמדם ספר? ulelamdam sefer? ואידך, ve'idach, and how
about what would the other one do with the five years for
the לוויים Levi'im who says it needs only three years? שאני הלכות
עבודה דתקיפין, shani hilchos avoda detkifin, no, it's the opposite, learning all
of the laws of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and how to
serve, that's extremely difficult. So there's one that says three, there's one
that says five. Which is the baseline and which one is the
exception? Either it's easier than normal or harder than normal. You do
wonder about the idea of five years for the לוויים Levi'im because
they were not doing the עבודה avoda of the כהנים, kohanim right?
If you were a כהן Kohen, and you needed five years, that's
one thing, you have to know all of the million details of
קרבנות, korbanos but here what do you have to know? A song
to sing? Maybe you have to work on your voice to master
it, you know, or so on, but... playing instruments?
Playing instruments, maybe that's it, becoming a master, but the language it
uses here is הלכות עבודה. hilchos avoda. הלכות עבודה hilchos avoda would
not was not really the purview of the כהנים, kohanim of the
לוויים, Levi'im, it was more of the כהנים.
kohanim Maybe only study during your מעמד?
ma'amad? What? Okay, what?
Maybe only study during your מעמד? ma'amad?
Oh, that's an interesting theory. Okay, the גמרא Gemara is not saying
that. Anyway, all right.
Okay, so what? So what do you think took them five years
then?
I have no idea. Now, so you've a babysitter right? All right.
Now, so we've established the difference between blemishes and years, and that
the the years is only an issue by אהל מועד, it's not
an issue in the future. I want to say a word about
what the logic of this difference is, okay, because for all the
times all these things we've been doing, this is the one where
it really does make sense to assume maybe the invalidities should apply
in in opposite ways. And the difference here is, you know,
to use a phrase, by the way, which is actually, you know,
taken from the imagery in the תורה Torah, that sometimes is used
nowadays to speak about people that serve in rabbinic types of posts,
is כלי קודש, klei kodesh, right? When the רמב"ם Rambam talks about
the laws relating to the כהנים, kohanim the רמב"ם Rambam says in
הלכות, hilchos, in his in the משנה תורה, Mishneh Torah, he says,
הלכות כלי המקדש והמשרתים בו, hilchos klei hamikdash vehamisharsim bo, something like
הלכות כלי המקדש והמשרתים בו, hilchos klei hamikdash vehamisharsim bo,
but anyway he combines the laws of the כהנים Kohanim? together with
the laws of the כלי שרת. klei shares. There is a concept,
right, in the תורה, Torah you know, that basically the כהנים Kohanim,
are like almost like holy vessels, they've been sanctified, they're they're used
in the מקדש Mikdash, and so on. If that's the concept that
applies to the כהנים, Kohanim. so you understand also the emphasis of
blemish, of מום, mum, although we might have problems with the idea
of why is there an emphasis in general about aesthetics and externals,
we certainly could acknowledge that that is a high concern of the
תורה Torah in the appearance of the מקדש, Mikdash everything is gold
and silver and beautiful, the aesthetics, the קרבנות korbanot, that are brought
are unblemished, everything that is sort of part of the objects of
the מקדש Mikdash and what is brought in the מקדש Mikdash. is
unblemished, so the כהן Kohen as well as one of the objects
of the מקדש, Mikdash one of the things that functions in the
מקדש is also something that has to be free of blemish. You
know, and there were a lot of ideas, by the way, about
this idea of the כהן kohen as a כלי שרת, kli shares,
like it says that the כהן kohen doesn't wear shoes, you might
remember from זבחים, why? Because the רצפה מקדשת, ritzpa mekadeshes, the floor,
his feet have to touch the floor because the sanctity of the
floor then connects to him and he becomes sanctified and that then
connects to the קרבן and so on, the whole idea that sometimes
we have בעצמו של כהן, be'atzmo shel Kohen, like the בדיקות, bedikos,
the body of the כהן, kohen. you know, so there's a lot
of these ideas of the כהן kohen as a type of holy
vessel where then when it becomes that, the aesthetics matter. The לוי
Levi is never seen as that. Although it is interesting, in this
פרשה where it speaks about twenty-five to fifty, it talks about how
do you dedicate the לוויים, Levi'im, it says you wave them, so
you are treating them as a type of a קרבן, but nevertheless
the לוויים Levi'im are much less the תורה Torah uses the words
קודש kodesh by the לוויים, Levi'im, and much more it uses the
word that they are נתונים נתונים. netunim netunim. נתונים נתונים הם לו.
netunim netunim hem lo. They are given over to serve, to serve
the כהנים, Kohanim. to assist the כהנים. Kohanim, The word לוי Levi
means right, you know, to like assist, to serve and so on.
So the לויים is much more about them as they do holy
service, but not as much as they being holy vessels and being
קודש. kodesh. As such, what invalidates them is not the aesthetic aspects
of a מום, mum, but the question of are they capable to
do the service. So, when the service was about carrying, right, a
big thing about being capable to do it is how old are
you. Now again, I don't know why thirty was the beginning, I
might have thought twenty should be the beginning, I don't know the
answer to that. But nevertheless, that's also the emphasis around the issue
of carrying. So the question is, well, capability, ability to do the
service, and that's determined by age, especially when the service is manual
labor. When the service is no longer manual labor, so as long
as their voice is still good, if their voice isn't good, they
do become פסול pasul because they can't do it, but as long
as their voice is good, as long as they can do their
service, age doesn't matter. So for לויים the whole question is, are
you qualified? Right, do you—are you able to do your job? And
for them it is the job that they are doing. Whereas for
כהנים Kohanim it is a whole—they're not only doing their job but
they're a holy vessel and therefore, you know, they're קודש kodesh and
therefore the issue of מום mum and blemish matters. Okay, so that
seems to be the real distinction here. For those that are interested,
רב Rav Soloveitchik in his שיעורים לזכר אבא מרי Shiurim Lezecher Abba
Mari develops this idea at length, the different sort of roles of
the כהנים—by Kohanim. the—he doesn't say roles, basically לוי Levi he says
is more about role and כהן kohen is more about just being
fully given over. That's why for example he points out that there's
this line that says that any כהן kohen that doesn't agree, you
know, agree
in principle to any one of the services of the כהונה, kehunah,
like he says I don't like the idea of eating the old
לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim or this or whatever he says, he's not
a valid כהן. Kohen Whereas by a לוי Levi we find the
opposite. By a לוי Levi we find that you are designated only
to play certain roles. Certain of the לויים work at the gates,
certain of them sing. If you're doing one role, you can't do
the other role. So he says this is exactly the difference. He
says if a כהן Kohen is basically given fully over, so if
there's one area that he has a reservation about, it's not like
he's been fully sanctified, fully given over. Whereas by a לוי Levi
it's about the job they're doing. So some are assigned to one
job and some are assigned to the other job and you don't
do the job that you're not assigned to. Okay, so this is
a major difference between כהנים Kohanim and לויים which works out very
well in terms of this question about invalidity or פסול.
psul. I would just say to the extent that לויים are performing
an official function and you know especially as part of a service
in the ritual, yes then I'd still say to that extent that
it should be a little bit like the כהנים Kohanim for you
know if you have a כהן Kohen, and you know he can't
have like three arms, let's say the לוי Levi has three arms
right you know and he's standing over and thinking.
So what you're concerned about is you're concerned about the aesthetics of
the people that are present, that even if you don't describe that
the object is the מקדש or the object is a כלי קודש,
keli kodesh, for the people that are present, the aesthetics are still
an issue. Okay, but let's say I don't like the fact that
you're bringing a קרבן together with me and that you look disgusting.
I mean you know and that you're you're disfigured right so in
a—so in a way I mean look for us and certainly I
think for our ethos the whole idea about physical disfigurement being a
problem is a hard thing to deal with in general right. So
the point is is that yes you're right the תורה Torah is
not ensuring that the environment is free from that it's only demanding
that the things that are sort of designated as you know as
holy objects don't have those problems.
Okay so let's keep on going. The גמרא Gemara says like this.
Is it only מום, mum, basically a bad voice?
Yeah a bad voice is a פסול psul by
the—I mean if—if you had a bad voice to begin with he
just wouldn't he wouldn't get off the ground.
Well the question is can you do the other עבודה? avodah? Because
לויים are designated as I said either for guard duty or for
singing, they don't cross over.
I see and like who determines what's a bad you know yeah.
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Okay our rabbis taught. כל מי שהביא שתי
שערות עד שיזקין. Kol mi she-hevi shetei searot ad she-yazkin. A כהן
Kohen is כשר kasher from the time he has two pubic hairs,
meaning he's an adult. So now we actually are seeing that כהנים
Kohanim although we said years don't invalidate that means like there's no
retirement age. Okay but you do have to be an adult before
you can serve. Until—from the time he has two pubic hairs until
he becomes old. כשר לעבודה Kasher la-avodah is good. ומומין פוסלין בו.
U-mumin poslin bo. And מומים mumin are a problem. Wait what's עד
שיזקין? ad she-yazkin? We'll talk about that. בן לוי. Ben Levi. Enough
questions we have twenty minutes left. בן לוי מבן שלשים ועד בן
חמשים כשר לעבודה. Ben Levi mi-ben shloshim ve-ad ben chamishim kasher la-avodah.
בן לוי Ben Levi from thirty to fifty again in the אהל
מועד. ושנים פוסלין בו. Ve-shanim poslin bo. And age you know is
a—is a retirement—invalidates, there's a retirement age. במה דברים אמורים. Bameh devarim
amurim. When is this true? באהל מועד שבמדבר. Be-ohel moed she-ba-midbar. In
the אהל מועד in the מדבר. midbar. אבל בשילה ובית עולמים. Aval
be-Shilo u-Veit Olamim. But when they are in the בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. אין נפסלים—here Ein nifsalim you go Michael—אלא בקול. ela be-kol. But
when they are in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, years is no
longer problem, singing voice is a problem. And it is beautiful as
I said the prompt for the לוי Levi is the capacity to
do the work. So when it's about carrying it's about are you
the right age. When it's about not about carrying it's about your
voice and are you able to do the singing and that is
the issue. Now. If that, I have to look at the Michael's
question about the issue about, you know, can you be assigned just
the guard duty and not the singing duty? But anyway, we have
a question, yes, from Dr.
Volis regarding voluntary versus conscripted.
You mean in terms of the other question about do you have
too many לויים serving?
If you get past if you're over 50. I see, it becomes
voluntary service as opposed to an obligation.
Oh, oh. That has never been said. You mean you want to
say that maybe once they get once they drop the 50, it's
not mandatory retirement, but it's voluntary retirement.
Yeah, that's interesting.
I've never seen that said, that like you can opt out after
a certain age. Yeah.
Wait wait wait but they say אבל לכל aval le-chol but that
wasn't that's just the לוי Levi part, not the כהן Kohen. part.
Right, right. We're the כהן Kohen part is still even בשיערות be-searot
with שתי שערות shtei searot and okay.
אמר רב יוסי, Amar Rav Yossi, מאי קרא, mai kra, what's the
verse say that you see that you have to that you have
to have a good voice? Because it says, ויהי כאחד למחצצרים ולמשוררים
להשמיע קול אחד. Vayehi ke-echad la-mechatztzerim vela-meshorerim le-hashmia kol echad. And they
will be like one, meaning sort of like a mingling of voices,
and for those that play the חצוצרות, chatzoztrot, right the musical the
trumpets or whatever they are, and those that sing, that they all
make one voice, meaning it's sort of like a symphony of voices.
Okay, so רש"י Rashi says the emphasis of ויהי כאחד, Vayehi ke-echad,
they're all like one, is coming to include even those that are
older. Again, by the way, notice that what they're also doing is
playing musical instruments. So our גמראס Gemaras that discuss how much is
the musical instrument central or not, and does it have to be
the לויים playing the musical instrument, certainly what's central for the לויים
is the is the singing with their voice. But that's another thing
that could potentially be a question, a role for the לויים, which
is not being focused on here. Okay, but I think the good
question, there are two good questions which I'll try to get back
to you on, which is one is what type of rotation did
they have for the לויים, was it the same twenty-four and the
other groups, and the other question about like if you can't do
the singing, can you still do the other roles? Okay, עד כאן
Ad kan back to a כהן, Kohein, כהן Kohein. is from the
time he's an adult until he gets elderly. Okay, so not a
specific year cutoff, but until he's considered too old. So what's too
old? Very old. עד כמה, Ad kama, how much? אמר רבי אילא
אמר רבי חנינא Amar Rabbi Ila amar Rabbi Chanina עד שירטב, ad
she-yiratev, until he trembles. So, you know, he cannot, I assume it
doesn't mean because of Parkinson's or something, but I just assume it
means that due to old age and infirmity, you know, he can't
hold his hand steady, which might also be a problem with קרבנות,
you might imagine. But it's not clear if the גמרא Gemara here,
again, is is translating that into an actual problem of doing the
job. It might just be that at that point you're just considered,
you know, there is a sense of being too old. Let's take
a look. It's not clear. תנן התם, Tenan hatam, we taught over
there. בעל קרי שטבל ולא הטיל מים, Baal keri she-taval velo hetil
mayim,
so you have somebody that had a seminal emission and he went
to the מקוה, mikvah, so now he's טהור. tahor. Okay, but he
did not urinate after he had had his seminal emission, after he
had ejaculated. So there's a concern that some a drop of semen
might still be left inside and then when he urinates it will
come out. So it says ולכשיטיל, u-le-chesheyatil, now when he urinates even
though he's been to the מקוה, mikvah, טמא, tamei, now he is
טמא tamei because now we assume that now semen came out, a
drop of semen came out with the urine. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi
Yossi omer, בחולה ובזקן טמא. be-choleh u-ve-zaken tamei.
That's only a problem if the person is elderly or sick that
you assume that not all the semen came out. בילד ובבריא, be-yeled
u-ve-viri,
but if the person is young and healthy, טהור, tahor, it's not
a problem then you assume that all of the semen came
out. ילד עד כמה, yeled ad kama, how young is considered, what
does it mean that you're young enough that this is not a
problem? אמר רבי אילא אמר רבי חנינא, Amar Rabbi Ila amar Rabbi
Chanina, כל שעומד על רגלו אחת וחולץ מנעלו ונועל מנעלו. kol she-omed
al raglo achat ve-choletz minalo ve-noel minalo.
See if you can do this. Stand on one leg and tie
your shoe, right?
This really is an issue of balance. I don't think it's an
issue of old age.
Like, I can sort of do it. I go like this.
I've done it before when there's a dirty place and there's nowhere
to sit. But so anyway, I think I sort of pass the
test. Anyway, okay. אמרו עליו על רבי חנינא, Amru alav al Rabbi
Chanina, they said about רבי חנינא, Rabbi Chanina, שהיה בן שמונים שנה,
she-haya ben shemonim shana, he was 80 years old, והיה עומד על
רגלו אחת וחולץ מנעלו ונועל מנעלו. ve-haya omed al raglo achat ve-choletz
minalo ve-noel minalo. He was able to stand, you see, so every
person is different in terms of how strong they are, to be
able to stand on one foot, take off his shoe, or put
on a shoe. No, this, yes,
this is the test for right. This is not exactly parallel to
our discussion about are you old too old to be a כהן.
Kohein, This is a question about do we assume that after ejaculation
there's still some might be some semen left. It's a very narrow
technical concern about that issue.
Right, well maybe, yeah exactly.
Okay, אמר רבי Amar Rabbi but I we're bringing it in because
it's another issue of using of determining old age based on not
a strict formal cutoff here but based on, you know, assessing each
person individual each person individually. I don't know, but it's assessing each
person individually similar to the idea of a כהן Kohein that it's
not a cutoff year but it's that you're, you know, you don't
tremble.
This is רבי חנינא סגן הכהנים, Rabbi Chanina Sgan HaKohanim, right?
Right, that's a good point. אמר רבי חנינא, Amar Rabbi Chanina, so
רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina said, חמין ושמן שסכתני אמי בילדותי. chamin ve-shemen
she-sachtani immi be-yalduti. the hot water and the oil that my mother
would anoint me with when I was young, הן עמדו לי בעת
זקנותי, hen amdu li beet ziknuti, they stood for me in my
old age, they gave me the health that even when I was
eighty years old, I was still able to pass that test. Okay,
but that's not exactly not related to a כהן, Kohen I mean
it's analogous, but it's not the same amount for a כהן. Kohen
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, so we've taught. Now we're dealing with other
ways in which age is relevant. It's a nice little גמרא. Gemara
You know, there's actually, it's quite interesting that there's very little סתם
stam here. You know, the סתם stam is usually like the, you
know, it's like the glue that ties together various Tannaic statements. Here
it's just juxtaposing different Tannaic statements where age matters without even having
like a narrative tying it together. Okay, so we had this one
issue about the about the טומאה tumah and now we have another.
תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: נתמלא זקנו, nitmalei zikno, when a person's beard
is filled out, ראוי לעשות שליח ציבור, raui laasot shaliach tzibbur, they
can become a representative of the community, ולירד לפני התיבה, vileyred lifnei
hateivah, to go down in front of the of the ark, meaning
to lead דאבנינג, davening, ולשא את כפיו, velisa et kapav, and to,
if the person is a כהן, Kohen to lift up the hands
to give the priestly blessing. Now, the issue by the way of
of שליח ציבור, shaliach tzibbur, we we would read as שליח ציבור
shaliach tzibbur means לירד לפני התיבה leyred lifnei hateivah to serve. But
רש"י Rashi says no, שליח ציבור shaliach tzibbur in this tense does
not mean just represent the ציבור tzibbur for דאבנינג; davening; it means
to actually be some type of a leader of the community. So
if you look at רש"י Rashi for לעשות שליח ציבור, laasot shaliach
tzibbur, רש"י Rashi says: לכל צרכיהם, lechol tzorcheihem, like four lines from
the top, or five lines from the narrow lines, לכל צרכיהם, lechol
tzorcheihem, לתקוע שופר, litkoah shofar, to blow a שופר, shofar, on presumably
on ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, ולנדות, velindot, to put people into excommunication,
very important service. So you're representing the community. Okay, ולמנות פרנס, velimnot
parnas, and to be appointed a type of פרנס, parnas, which is
a a lay leader. So for רש"י Rashi this is not just
about serving in the synagogue, but it's also about a certain age
of, you know, that a respectful age that it's appropriate to be
seen as a leader of the community. So again, by the way,
you know, it's not like well, נתמלא זקנו, nitmalei zikno, but means
you're not thirteen where you have that away. Presumably there are other
qualifications as well, you know, like for example we mentioned the voice
by the לויים. If you look at the different גמרות Gemorot that
discuss the requirements for what we would call a שליח ציבור, shaliach
tzibbur, חזן, chazan, and so on, you know, they speak about being
a certain age, being married, nobody is angry at him and so
on. Among all those lists, what you don't find is a requirement
that he has a nice voice. So,
so some people try to say, well, there's also a requirement that
everybody is happy with him, so that sort of requires that he
has a nice voice. Others say no, if he doesn't have a
nice voice, he's not even a חזן. chazan. So this assumes he's
a חזן, chazan, what are the criteria. Anyway, so here the issue
of a certain minimum age to be, if you are representing the
community in some lay function or in some ritual
function, it's not enough that you're technically בר מצוה. Bar Mitzvah. There
has to be a certain age where you're considered to be old
enough, mature enough, that it's respectful for the community for you to
serve. Okay. מאימתי כשר לעבודה? meimatai kasher laavodah?
When can a person serve be begin to be, a כהן Kohen
begin to be כשר לעבודה? kasher laavodah? משיביא שתי שערות, mishayavi shtei
searot,
from the time that he has two pubic hairs, he's an adult.
רבי אומר, Rebbi omer, אומר אני, omer ani, I say, עד בן
עשרים, ad ben esrim, no, he has to be twenty years old
to be כשר. kasher. It is not enough to just technically be
an adult. This is about שליח ציבור
shaliach tzibbur or even for כהנים?
Kohanim Now that we're back to כהנים, Kohanim we're back to כהנים.
Kohanim Okay. Not clear. We haven't
discussed. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, מאי טעמא דרבי? mai taama
d'Rebbi? What's the reason of רבי? Rebbi? דכתיב, the verse says, ויעמידו
את הלוים מבן עשרים שנה
ומעלה, vayaamidu et haLeviim miben esrim shanah vamalah, they they appointed or
whatever the לויים from twenty years up, לנצח על מלאכת בית ה',
lenatzeach al melechet Beit Hashem,
to be מנצח menatzeach on the work of בית ה'. Beit Hashem.
Now what does מנצח menatzeach mean? למנצח lamnatzeach you would right, למנצח
lamnatzeach like it says למנצח lamnatzeach with דוד, David, right, מזמור לדוד,
mizmor leDavid, it could refer to a type of, some people think
mean translate as the choir master, and translate as playing certain types
of musical instruments. As such it would be referring to the לויים.
The problem here is that the context of this discussion, although not
explicit, is implicit, and we're going to say it explicitly in a
minute, is about the כהנים. Kohanim So לנצח lenatzeach here, right if
you take a look, I think רש"י Rashi? says, where's רש"י? Rashi
לנצח, lenatzeach, משמע לעבוד עבודת כבדות הצריכה ניצוח, mashma laavod avodat kvedut
hatzrichah nitzuach, like heavy work that requires, you know, victory, like strength,
courage, courageous work or work of strength. So I'm not exactly sure,
somehow they're reading this in the context of working in the מקדש.
לנצח lenatzeach to to gird your strength for the working in בית
ה'. Beit Hashem. So you need to be twenty. ואידך, veidach, no.
לנצח lenatzeach שאני. shani. The others says no, that's not your standard
work of the כהנים, Kohanim this is the work of the כהנים
Kohanim maybe in the building of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash in
the time of עזרא, Ezra, but it is not a standard requirement
for כהנים. Kohanim to be twenty years old. So now the Gemara
(גמרא) Gemara goes on, v'hai kra b'leviyim ksiv (והאי קרא בלוים כתיב).
v'hai kra b'leviyim ksiv How could we be bringing this into a
discussion of Kohanim (כהנים)? Kohanim It says Leviyim (לוים). Leviyim So says
Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi (רבי יהושע בן לוי), Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi
like Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi. D'amar Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi (דאמר רבי
יהושע בן לוי), d'amar Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi b'esrim v'arba mekomot nikru
Kohanim Leviyim (בעשרים וארבע מקומות נקראו כהנים לוים). b'esrim v'arba mekomot nikru
Kohanim Leviyim There are twenty-four places where the Torah says Leviyim (לוים)
Leviyim and it really is referring to Kohanim (כהנים). Kohanim V'zeh echad
mehem (וזה אחד מהם), v'zeh echad mehem this is one
of them. VehaKohanim haLeviyim bnei Tzadok (והכהנים הלוים בני צדוק). vehaKohanim haLeviyim
bnei Tzadok The Kohanim the Levites the sons of Tzadok. And Tzadok
(צדוק) Tzadok obviously was a Kohen (כהן), Kohen so Levi (לוי) Levi
here means Kohen (כהן). Kohen Now why are Kohanim (כהנים) Kohanim called
Leviyim (לוים)? Leviyim So the obvious answer is because they're also Leviyim
(לוים), Leviyim that's the tribe they were a part of. But Rashi
(רש"י) Rashi says here, Rashi (רש"י) Rashi says another explanation is that
Levi (לוי) Levi means to serve. Okay so Kohen (כהן) Kohen also
means to serve, right? Likhahein (לכהן). likhahein But Rashi (רש"י) Rashi also
says that Levi (לוי) Levi can mean to serve, so therefore Rashi
(רש"י) says, v'ani shamati lashon Leviyim
shamashim (ואני שמעתי לשון לוים שמשים), v'ani shamati lashon Leviyim shamashim how
would we say that, a shamash (שמש), shamash how would we say
that? Sexton? Okay, people that serve. Kmo v'yilavu alecha v'ishartucha (כמו וילוו
עליך וישרתוך). kmo v'yilavu alecha v'ishartucha They shall accompany you, because the
Leviyim (לוים) Leviyim accompany and serve, assist, maybe assist is a better
word than serve. Kohen (כהן) Kohen is to serve, Levi (לוי) is
to assist. Okay so the Kohanim (כהנים) are also assistants, they assist
in the Mikdash (מקדש). So anyway the simpler explanation though is because
Kohanim (כהנים) are also Leviyim (לוים). Leviyim So what do we know?
We have said that the Kohanim (כהנים), we have said that Kohanim
(כהנים) it is Leviyim (לוים) Leviyim it is age that is a
problem when they were carrying. Now age is not a problem, it's
only an issue about voice. Interestingly as Michael points out, now that
it's only an issue of voice, is age at all for Leviyim
(לוים)? Leviyim Do they have to be Bar Mitzvah (בר מצוה)? Bar
Mitzvah Is there a cutoff age? We don't know. The only thing
now mentioned is voice. And by Kohanim (כהנים) we of course keep
the invalidity of blemishes, but we've also added that they have to
be Bar Mitzvah (בר מצוה) Bar Mitzvah or maybe twenty, and the
cutoff age is getting too old which means trembling and so on.
Tosfos (תוספות) Tosfos discusses the question because if anybody notices when they
do Birkas Kohanim (ברכת כהנים), Birkas Kohanim the kids go up with
their fathers, right? Here we're saying at most thirteen, right? At most
well meaning right the youngest possible age is thirteen. How do you
get below that? So Tosfos (תוספות) Tosfos says actually there's a contradiction
in different Gemaras (גמרות) Gemaras about whether a somebody can do Nesi'as
Kapayim (נשיאת כפים) nesi'as kapayim less than Bar Mitzvah (בר מצוה) Bar
Mitzvah and that the way Tosfos (תוספות) Tosfos resolves it and we
resolve it is actually whether it means whether you're going up alone
or going up with an adult. If there are already adults going
up, then if you're younger you can go up. But alone, as
we've seen before, part of the concern is sort of the respect
of the community and how old is the person that they have
serving them or giving the blessing. So if they have people of
the right age giving the blessing, a Levi (לוי), a Kohen (כהן)
can accompany. But that Tosfos (תוספות) Tosfos says about Birkas Kohanim (ברכת
כהנים). Birkas Kohanim Big question if that would apply for example about
the work in the Beis HaMikdash (בית המקדש). Beis HaMikdash There it
seems that we are very strict in terms of either the thirteen
or the twenty cutoff. Even if there are others in the congregation
was ten you wouldn't... right? Well no you do a you do
Birkas Kohanim (ברכת כהנים) Birkas Kohanim even if he's one of the
minyan (מנין)...
minyan if he's the only one. If the katan (קטן) katan
is the only Kohen (כהן). Yes, but if there's an adult Kohen
(כהן) then the katan
(קטן) katan goes with him. Okay, so now the Gemara (גמרא) Gemara.
wraps up, so let's take a look. Tano rabbanan (תנו רבנן), Tano
rabbanan ish m'zaracha l'dorotam (איש מזרעך לדורותם), ish m'zaracha l'dorotam any person
from your seed for future generations. Okay so this is this is
the psukim (פסוקים) that say that a blemish invalidates by a Kohen
(כהן). But what does a blemish invalidate? It invalidates an ish (איש),
ish once you're already a man. If you're not even a man
yet, you don't even have to worry about blemishes. So that's how
we know that you have to be an adult or thirteen. Mekan
amar Rabbi Eliezer katan pasul l'avodah (מכאן אמר רבי אליעזר קטן פסול
לעבודה). mekan amar Rabbi Eliezer katan pasul l'avodah A minor is invalid
and even tam (תם), tam even unblemished. That blemishes are a problem
once you're an ish (איש). ish If you're not an ish (איש),
ish we don't even have to talk about blemishes. M'eimatai kasher l'avodah
(מאימתי כשר לעבודה)? m'eimatai kasher l'avodah What is the minimum age? M'sheyavi
shtei se'arot (משיביא שתי שערות). m'sheyavi shtei se'arot Technically from the time
that you are have two pubic hairs, you are considered halachically (הלכתית)
halachically an adult, Bar Mitzvah (בר מצוה). Bar Mitzvah Aval echav haKohanim
(אבל אחיו הכהנים) aval echav haKohanim ein manichin oto l'avodah ad sheyei
ben esrim (אין מניחין אותו לעבודה עד שיהא בן עשרים). ein manichin
oto l'avodah ad sheyei ben esrim So this is similar to Rebbi
(רבי), Rebbi although we'll try to figure that out in a minute,
that even though technically you're allowed, the other Kohanim (כהנים) don't want
a kid doing the avodah (עבודה). avodah They prevent people from doing
the avodah (עבודה) avodah until they're more of an adult, until they're
twenty. Just I think respect for their job. So the Gemara (גמרא)
says, ika d'amri ha Rebbi hi (איכא דאמרי הא רבי היא), ika
d'amri ha Rebbi hi some say that this is Rebbi's (רבי) Rebbi
position, you have to be twenty. Ve'afilu psul d'rabbanan leit leh (ואפילו
פסול דרבנן לית ליה), ve'afilu psul d'rabbanan leit leh and when Rebbi
(רבי) Rebbi said twenty, he wasn't even saying the twenty is an
invalidity. Not even less than twenty, not even it's not even a
rabbinic (דרבנן) d'rabbanan problem. It's just a communal problem, the fellow Kohanim
(כהנים) don't like it, but it's not a technical problem. Ve'ika d'amri
(ואיכא דאמרי), ve'ika d'amri some say no, Rebbi isa psul mi-d'rabbanan (רבי
אית ליה פסול מדרבנן). Rebbi isa psul mi-d'rabbanan Rebbi (רבי) Rebbi says
twenty actually less than twenty is invalid, at least rabbinically. It's a
real invalidity at least at a rabbinic level. Ve-ha (והא), this that
says twenty is a problem because of the other Kohanim (כהנים). Rabbanan
hi (רבנן היא), rabbanan hi that's the Rabbis (רבנן). U'l'chatchilah hu d'lo
(ולכתחילה הוא דלא), u'l'chatchilah hu d'lo that's only a problem l'chatchilah (לכתחילה)
l'chatchilah because the other Kohanim (כהנים) don't want you to. But there's
no technical problem, not even at a rabbinic level. Aval b'di'eved avodato
ksheirah (אבל בדיעבד עבודתו כשרה). aval b'di'eved avodato ksheirah B'di'eved (בדיעבד) b'di'eved
it is valid. Okay so what you see here interesting about this
end discussion, and I think it came up before about the Gemara
(גמרא) about having a full... I think it came up before about
the גמרא about having a full beard before you are supposed to
be a חזן chazzan is that there's some things where the issue
of age is an issue of respect for the people you're serving
or working with. Right, the fellow כהנים if they think you know
this is a very חשוב chashuv thing, who wants a kid? I
got to tell you, you know, I think we feel that I
feel that sometimes especially like if you have somebody, you know, very
young on ימים נוראים Yamim Noraim leading the services. They might have
a beautiful voice, you know, but sometimes it does not feel that
that's the appropriate for the respect of the community that such a
young person is playing this role at such, you know, in such
a sort of, you know, significant moment for the community and in
the דאווענען. davening. So I think that's interesting that the invalidity of
age we had been talking about the question about whether you can
do the work or not, but there's another question here which has
to do with the not at one end of the spectrum being
the old end of the spectrum but at the young end of
the spectrum of the question about sort of the respect for the
people you're serving or for the people you're working with. All right,
how do you present this section to your students? It's not yet
in the curriculum but give me the question about the what does
it mean to be a young rabbi? Is that your question? I
mean I think that that's how do you apply it? Well I'm
wondering what you're looking at the text but you drew a connection
so I'm wondering what connection you're drawing. The question about what I
mean I'm assuming the connection you're drawing is what does it mean
to be a young rabbi when you're serving people that are much
more experienced and much older than you. I mean that's an issue
that we do discuss. I mean the problem here about, you know,
even the שליח ציבור shliach tzibbur issue is not everybody is always
מקפיד makpid on these שליח ציבור shliach tzibbur things, you know, some
people do have people, right, if you I mean like a kid
בר מצווה, bar mitzvah, these are שליח ציבור shliach tzibbur and he's
not he's יורד לפני התיבה, yored lifnei hateivah, he doesn't satisfy those
criteria. So you know there are also questions about, you know, community
standards and what, you know, and how those standards can be readjusted
based on the community's own sort of, you know, its own parameters,
its own issues. But no, the questions about what does it mean
to be a young person serving people that are certainly much older
and more experienced than you and you know those are those are
issues. Okay let's just do a little bit more, we have only
two-three minutes. טהור בכלי חרס טמא בכל הכלים. Tahor bikli cheres tamei
bechol hakeilim. I thought we were going to get through this דף
one two three today. I know when there's not when it was
rich in discussion not necessarily okay but challenging in terms of the
concept. טהור בכלי חרס טמא בכל הכלים טהור בכל הכלים טמא בכלי
חרס. Tahor bikli cheres tamei bechol hakeilim, tahor bechol hakeilim tamei bikli
cheres. The types of ways in which a pottery vessel is טהור
tahor is interesting you because logically you should be saying the opposite
like the previous משנה but okay prevent does not become טמא tamei
would make other vessels become טמא tamei and the way other vessels
do not become טמא tamei would make a pottery vessel טמא. tamei.
What does that mean? So let's just begin this in the גמרא.
תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: אויר כלי חרס טמא וגבו טהור. Avir kli
cheres tamei vegabo tahor. The inner part, the air of a pottery
vessel is טמא, tamei, the back of it is טהור. tahor. אויר
כל הכלים טהור וגבן טמא. Avir kol hakeilim tahor vegaban tamei. And
the reverse is true by non-pottery vessels. What's the law? A normal
vessel, the way it becomes טמא tamei is through contact. Okay, so
you have a dead bug or whatever it is, it touches the
back of my Pyrex bowl or of my pot or it touches
the inside of it, some form of contact makes it טמא. tamei.
But by pottery vessels contact doesn't matter, what matters is that something
is present in the אויר, avir, the air but there's got to
be a better word the air, the volume, you know, of the
vessel itself. The contained space of the vessel. So even if a
dead rodent was suspended in mid-air inside the vessel, it would be
טהור tahor I mean sorry even suspended it would be טמא. tamei.
However, if that rodent touched on the outside, it would be טהור.
tahor. So if it touched on the inside? If it touched on
the inside, it's טמא tamei only because it was present on the
inside. Touching doesn't matter. So what causes so normally the difference is
framed as outside is a problem for other vessels, inside for pottery
vessels but that's imprecise. The real difference is touching is a problem
for all other vessels and for pottery vessels it is presence in
the inner space of the vessel. Okay so let's just read a
little bit more on this and wrap up. נמצא, Nimtza, so you
see that טהור בכלי חרס טמא בכל הכלים, tahor bikli cheres tamei
bechol hakeilim, what's טהור tahor for כלי חרס kli cheres touch is
טמא tamei for other כלים. keilim. טהור בכל הכלים, Tahor bechol hakeilim,
what's טהור tahor for other כלים keilim being suspended on the inside,
טמא בכלי חרס tamei bikli cheres is a problem for pottery vessels.
והני מילי מנא לן? Vahani mili mena lan? Where do we know
this from? דתנו רבנן we taught תוכו, tocho, it says כל אשר
בתוכו, kol asher betocho, everything in it. It says in the תורה
it will become טמא, tamei, this is said by a pottery vessel.
So in it ואף על פי שלא נגע, veaf al pi shelo
naga, even if it doesn't touch, just its presence in it. אתה
אומר אף על פי שלא נגע Ata omer af al pi shelo
naga or או אינו אלא אם כן נגע? o eino ela im
kein naga? Maybe it means it's inside and it's touching? רבי יונתן
בן אבטולמוס אומר, Rabbi Yonasan ben Abtolmos omer, נאמר תוכו לטמא, ne'emar
tocho letamei, it says anything in it becomes טמא, tamei, ונאמר תוכו
ליטמא, vane'emar tocho leitamei, and it says that if there's a bug
in a pottery vessel it makes the vessel Not a bug, a
rodent—it makes the vessel טמא. tame. מה תוכו האמור ליטמא, ma tocho
ha-amur litame, when it says inside of it, when it says becoming
טמא, tame, אף על פי שלא נגע, af al pi she-lo naga,
even if that object didn't touch, we'll say why in a minute,
אף תוכו האמור ליטמא, af tocho ha-amur litame, even when something is
in the vessel to make the vessel טמא, tame, אף על פי
שלא נגע, af al pi she-lo naga, even though it doesn't touch.
והא מנלן, ve-ha minalan, how do you know foods in the vessel
become טמא tame even though they're not touching the wall? אמר רבי
יונתן, Amar Rabbi Yonatan, Rabbi Yonatan says, התורה העידה על כלי חרס,
ha-Torah he-ida al klei cheres, the Torah testified that a כלי חרס
klei cheres makes טמא tame things inside it, ואפילו מלא חרדל, ve-afilu
malei chardal, even if it is filled with mustard seeds. Anybody seen
mustard seeds? Tiny little things. Think like it says coriander seeds. So
basically poppy seeds. So the Torah says anything in the pottery vessel
becomes טמא. tame. Well how does it happen? Anything. So let's say
your pottery vessel is filled with poppy seeds, right? So it touches,
what does it make טמא? tame? What's touching it? The things on
the outer rim. How do all the million seeds on the inside
become טמא? tame? And you can't say they transfer, because once the
food is טמא, tame, it doesn't transfer beyond it, certainly doesn't go
beyond a שני. sheini. How does one seed make a million other
seeds טמא? tame? So it's really not through contact, it's through presence
on the inside of a vessel. So since we know that by
a pottery vessel, the things that become טמא tame are because they're
present on the inside, even though they're not touching, we also say
the reverse, that when a טמא tame thing makes the vessel טמא,
tame, it is not because it is touching, but because it is
present on the inside.